Guide to the Ben Russak papers, 1935-1942
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
Ben Russak papers,
1935-1942
C0221
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
2.25 linear feet (5 boxes)
The Ben Russak papers is a collection of Federal Theatre Project and Federal Writers' Project material collected by Ben Russak from 1935 to 1942. The papers include playscripts and publications created by the Federal Theatre Project, as well as pamphlets and collections of folklore material created by the Federal Writers' Project.
Russak, Ben.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Papers donated to Special Collections and Archives by Ben Russak on March 26 and April 17, 1979.
Scope and Content
The Ben Russak papers is a collection of Federal Theatre Project and Federal Writers' Project material collected by Ben Russak from 1935 to 1942. The papers include playscripts and publications created by the Federal Theatre Project, as well as pamphlets and collections of folklore material created by the Federal Writers' Project. The collection is divided into two series based on origination of the material. Series one consists of material from the Federal Theatre Project and includes playscripts, magazine publications, and folk songs. Series two consists of material from the Federal Writers' Project including manuscripts, Nebraska folklore, and research pamphlets.
Related Material
The Works Progress Administration oral histories collection, the Federal Theatre Project collection, the Federal Theatre Project photograph collection, as well as numerous other personal papers.
Historical Information
The Federal Theatre Project was a division of the Works Progress Administration (WPA), which provided employment for large numbers of artists, writers, and performers during the Great Depression (1929-1939). The Federal Theatre began in 1935 and, until its end in 1939, flourished as the first and only federally sponsored and subsidized theater program in the United States. Directed by Hallie Flanagan (1880-1969), it was a way for theatrical professionals to gain employment during the Depression.
Arrangement
Collection is organized into two series. Each series is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Series 1: Federal Theatre Project, 1935-1939 (Boxes 1-4)
Series 2: Federal Writers' Project, 1937-1942 (Boxes 4-5)
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Federal Theatre Project (U.S.); Federal Writers' Project.
Subjects:
New Deal, 1933-1939.; Theater--United States.
Contents List
- Series 1: Federal Theatre Project, 1935-1939; (3.5 boxes)
  Series one consists of material from the Federal Theatre Project and includes playscripts, magazine publications, and folk songs.
  - Ballads and songs from broadsides 1773-1776, February 3, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Better Sort playscript, February 1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brother Mose playscript, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chalk Dust playscript, September 1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Donogoo, September 1937 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Excursion, September 1937 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Federal Theatre Magazine (volume I number I), November 25, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Folk music in America, June 1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Folk songs mainly from West Virginia, June 1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Folk songs of America, December 1938 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Folk tunes from Mississippi, July 1937 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Folk tunes from Mississippi, July 1937 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Generations (Yiddish playscript), 1930s (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Haven playscript (reissue), February 1938 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Help Yourself playscript, November 1936 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Injunction Granted playscript, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - It Can't Happen Here playscript, September 18, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Magazine of Art, January 1937 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - The Man of the Times playscript, 1930s (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1935 playscript, October 16, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Power playscript, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Precious Land playscript, February 1937 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Program of the Federal Arts Projects, June 25-July 1, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Prologue to Glory playscript, May 1938 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - The Second Shepherd's Play playscript, October 1937 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Southwestern folk history (Oklahoma), May 27, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - The Theatre Abroad (volume I, number VI), May 1939 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Theatre of the gold rush decade in San Francisco, 1930s (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Traditional ballads mainly from West Virginia, March 1939 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Triple A Plowed Under playscript, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Series 2: Federal Writers' Project, 1937-1942; (1.5 boxes)
  Series two consists of material from the Federal Writers' Project including manuscripts, Nebraska folklore, and research pamphlets.
  - Balance in (square dances, Kentucky), October 1942 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - The builders of timberline lodge, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Conference on contemporary culture, November 16-17, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Hoosier folklore bulletin (Indiana), December 1942 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - MSS...manuscripts - Federal Writers Project (South Dakota), circa 1930s (Box 4, Folder 6)
    3 issues - February, March, and September, of a periodical for and by WPA writers and workers prepared and published "after hours" by members of the state staff, Federal Writers Project in Pierre, South Dakota.
  - Nebraska folklore pamphlets (numbers 1 to 18), 1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Nebraska folklore: Animal legends, August 1, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Nebraska folklore: Ballads, October 1938 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Nebraska folklore: Children's games, September 1, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Nebraska folklore: Children's singing games, June 1, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Nebraska folklore: Cowboy songs, May 15, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Nebraska folklore: Cowboy songs, November 1, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Nebraska folklore: Farmers' alliance songs of the 1890's, December 1938 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Nebraska folklore: Historical legends, June 15, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Nebraska folklore: Indian ghost legends, November 15, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Nebraska folklore: Indian place legends, May 29, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Nebraska folklore: More Santee-Sioux Indian legends, October 1939 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Nebraska folklore: Nebraska cattle brands, November 1938 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Nebraska folklore: Pioneer recollections, January 1940 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Nebraska folklore: Proverbs, prophesies, signs and sayings, October 1, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Nebraska folklore: Proverbs, prophesies, signs and sayings (part II), October 15, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Nebraska folklore: Reminiscences of Dad Streeter, February 1939 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Nebraska folklore: Songs about Nebraska, September 1938 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Nebraska folklore: Tall tales, July 1938 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - New Jersey volume II research pamphlets (Federal Writers Project), 1937 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Over the Turquoise trail (volume I, number I and II), 1930s (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - We ain't down yet (song), 1930s (Box 5, Folder 5)